soft ng radio episode 134 interview with
Michael Nygaard this is software
engineering radio the podcast for
professional developers on the web at s
e - radio dotnet
I see radio brings you relevant and
detailed discussions and interviews on
software engineering topics every 10
days thanks to our audience and the
partners listed on our website for
support
[Music]
welcome listeners to another episode of
software engineering radio this is I
think interview number six recorded at
this year's Joe and we're going to talk
about a book that's actually it has
something in common with another book we
talked about it's the second book on
software I've seen which has a glider on
the cover and of course I think that's
because the book is called release it
and of course the glider has a release
handle to release the tow towing cable
and our guest of course is the author of
this book Michael Nygaard hi Michael I
am very glad to be here
I'm glad we can get you on so um well
the obvious first question please talk
about yourself so our audience knows who
you are sure I'm an architect and
developer of application software have
been for nearly 20 years at this point
I've done work in many different domains
military scientific engineering
industrial education finance and for the
last 10 years or so a lot of retail work
through somewhat bizarre set of
circumstances about five years ago I
ended up moving into a group that does
operations for software that we didn't
write right so while I've always
followed my own software into production
now I get to take accountability for
software produced by other people as
well so you feel the pain absolutely
yeah so this is already a little bit of
an introduction how you came to write
this book so please give us an overview
of what the book is about many people
might probably know it actually we got
requests to specifically get you on the
show so at least those people know the
book oh yeah please give us a I don't
know ten thousand feet overview of what
the book contains and how you came to
write it well what I what I learned
receiving software into production and
being the person who gets called at 3:00
in the morning when it doesn't work what
I learned is that the software we tend
to produce isn't all that well-suited
for living in the real world the world
of production is is where it ultimately
matters and I came to believe that all
of our material on design and
architecture all of that is aimed at the
moment of passing QA it's aimed at the
functional requirements right yeah but
it isn't aimed at surviving in
production and to me this seemed
analogous to to the aiming for the birth
of a baby while making no preparation
for that child's life as a human being
after the moment of birth mm-hmm yeah so
then the book is about how to write
software in a way that the operations
guys are happy is that the fair
assumption or is that a little bit too
small a scope that's that's definitely
one way to read it yeah but it's not
just the operations guys of course our
sponsors the people who pay for our
software are really much more interested
in how it does in production than how
well it passes QA you can pass QA on
your your first regression test with
flying colors and ultimately no one will
care if it doesn't run in production mhm
okay so I guess you know going down from
10,000 feet to let's say seven thousand
feet if we look at the structure of the
book and hence at the structure of this
topic at the overall problem space is
there a way to structure it you know in
a couple of sections that we might then
discuss in the rest of the podcast yeah
I built the book in sort of priority
order of trying to deal with the worst
problems first hence the first part of
the book is all about stability because
if your software is not stable in
production then it doesn't matter how
well it performs and it doesn't matter
how well it can be changed in the future
yeah so the first section of the book is
about stability and in each of these
sections I introduced with a a case
study I've been told that these these
read like detective stories which was
kind of what I had in mind that these
should be you know first-person
real-life examples of things that
happened at actual companies yeah though
i disguised all the names
for obvious reasons yep and then then
the other aspects are just to you know
to give an overview of what's coming in
the rest of the episode after stability
we have after stability we have a
section on capacity because once you've
stabilized your system the next most
common complaint I've observed
that it doesn't perform well enough for
it can't handle enough concurrent users
yeah so stability again I introduced
with a case study and then I have a
number of anti patterns common things
that I see people doing to harm their
capacity and then patterns that you can
apply to to improve capacity even on the
infrastructure you've got right okay so
I'm not specifically addressing
scalability which would be the ability
to add more resources right but I am
addressing maximizing the value of the
resources you have and section threes
then I guess stuff you can put into the
system to really make the operations
guys happy so they can monitor the
system and understand what's going on
right yeah exactly I found a lot of the
software that we were receiving into
operations exhibited what I called sick
goldfish syndrome when you have a sick
goldfish that's going to live or it's
going to die but there's bugger all you
can do about it in the meantime you just
wait to see if it goes belly-up it we
have to put in the ability to know
what's going on inside the system and so
that's what what that part is about okay
I also talked about how to build it so
that operators don't inadvertently make
mistakes and do bad things to you okay
okay so let's look at the first of those
stability and I guess it's a good idea
to first define what you mean by the
term I've used stability as the
consistent long term availability of the
features that your users care about okay
so I approach everything with the
assumption that your users don't
actually care whether the server's up
and running I've tried to explain about
deadlocks and hung threads and how the
Java Virtual Machine is still running
but it's just not doing anything because
all the locks are held that argument
never really seems to work they still
keep saying that the site has crashed
right because to all externally
observable behavior it is crashed yeah
and so but I also want to take the
perspective that sometimes you will have
partial functionality available we build
complex systems we
integration out to you know significant
portions of the internet and other parts
of the enterprise in any you know
reasonably sized company and so it's
very often the case that some computer
somewhere is malfunctioning and
therefore I can't do the normal function
of my application but I may be able to
preserve partial functionality and serve
some users well graceful degradation
right absolutely yeah and I guess also
the other thing is that usually a
failure one failure is typically not
enough you have to particularly you know
chains of failures or a couple of you
know bad circumstances happening at the
same time and that brings down the whole
system so understanding those chains and
those dependencies is probably also an
important aspect it is although usually
you can only identify those chains in
retrospect yeah as a post-mortem yes yes
and they always seem perfectly obvious
then but yeah of course very difficult
to predict the state space is so large
and every every external integration
adds new dimensions to the state space
yeah which brings us to the first set
well to the first of the anti patterns
ie things you you can do wrong so well
you do them right in the sense that they
whatever if you do these things the
chances for stability are lower yes
that's the definition of what the any
patterns are can you give us a little
bit an overview of what some of those
are maybe they're I don't know top three
or four and maybe help us understand
some of those sure well the first anti
pattern that I talked about and and what
I consider the number one risk to
stability is integration points
I think our systems would be much
happier if they didn't have to integrate
with any other systems yeah but of
course a standalone program isn't very
interesting these days yeah so in a
sense integration points are a necessary
evil yeah but I want everybody to regard
them as inherently dangerous to the
stability of our own software and so I
go through a number of examples in cases
where even seemingly innocuous things
like database calls can cause our
application to hang
beyond the textbook deadly embrace I
yeah can you give us an example of one
of those I mean how does a database
query you know related or result in such
a problem well you could have a
situation I call a cross tier deadlock
so because we're dealing with multiple
threads we always have to consider that
in a cross tier deadlock one thread is
holding a lock on a row in the database
and needs a connection from a connection
pool the second connection pool is
likely exhausted and perhaps one of the
threads that holds a connection in that
pool could release it if only it could
get a lock on that row in the database
so we have one thread which is blocked
in the application tier and another one
which is blocked in the database tier
there's no server in the world that will
detect that all right okay so the easy
way out of that one is if you only ever
have to have one connection pool yeah
and you're only ever speaking to one
database now again that's sort of a
tough constraint to meet these days yeah
yeah the other anti-pattern I found
actually quite funny is users
well users are very harmful to a system
yeah I detected that already before so
unfortunately like integration points
are also necessary a couple of ways that
users can cause problems it's not so
much individual users who cause problems
but it's the masses of them so we we had
this term the Slashdot effect from 90s
but these days the Slashdot effect is is
a trivial bump the real dangerous sites
or ones cnn.com yeah anything that goes
on cnn.com is very likely to crash to
dot because stories go up at a moment in
time and so large numbers of people find
out about the site at a moment in time
and pretty much all of our applications
and application servers deal badly with
getting too many users approaching this
item at once ya know so huge amounts of
uses are the actual problem not users
themselves right okay so another one
maybe the the last one that sounds
really interesting
kind of non-obvious is the SLA inversion
SLA standing for service letter
agreement yes what's that about
so SLA s are hugely important to IT
operations
they're usually if internal to the
company they're evaluated on their
ability to deliver SLA s the executives
are you know called on the carpet if
they're not delivering the correct SLA s
and so we often are asked to make
promises with really no way to to back
them up right yeah
a sulli inversion is an anti-pattern
that occurs when a system is expected to
deliver a very high SLA and yet it has
dependencies on other systems of lesser
SLA it's okay and even if it has
dependencies on other systems of the
same SLE because we expect failures in
those dependent systems to be
uncorrelated our SLA would be not the
not just the minimum of our dependent
set but our SLA would actually be the
product of the SLA s of all of our
dependency so when you take a look at at
a system with a typical number of
integrations and dependencies you can
easily get your SLA down to you know 90
to 90 88% very quickly particularly we
also often have hidden dependencies on
things like enterprise services such as
LDAP or DNA yeah these are you know not
normally sort of accounted for when
we're drawing our architecture diagrams
that just the substrate of the network
yeah and they also tend to be handled
badly by IT DNS servers are often you
know spark 20 pizza boxes sitting under
the network admins desk we talked a
little bit about the anti-patterns which
is stuff you shouldn't do I guess you
could argue that it's more important to
understand the stuff you should do so
let's look a little bit at some of the
patterns sure so first I do want to say
though that I think there's a lot of
value in understanding where the
problems lie and even just knowing about
them helps you of right I think some of
the issues the
the stability patterns are solutions
that I've seen that address classes of
problems so one of them that that I
think is particularly significant is
what I call the circuit breaker pattern
this is a component inside of an
application that counts failures perhaps
using something like a leaky bucket
Proctor yeah and we talked about that in
the Bob hanmer episode so you might want
to go back and listen to that so if the
circuit breaker counts too many fail too
many failures in an integration point
for a given unit of time it cuts off
that feature right I believe that this
is a better way of approaching failures
in integrations than the typical sort of
retry loop if you think about a retry
loop if you're calling a back-end system
that's degraded your timing out and a
retry loop just means you're going to
incur multiple timeouts right which
hurts your system because it means
you're now responding slowly to your
users so somebody else's problem is
becoming your problem now and it hurts
the backend system we already postulated
that it's degraded and so when it's
degraded is exactly when we're gonna hit
it even harder which doesn't really make
sense yeah instead the circuit breaker
attempts to understand the global state
and cut off that call when it's not
going to succeed all right all right
just give up basically and forget about
that part for a while yeah for a while
yeah okay timeouts are obviously related
right you should never try to talk to
any other system without giving it a
time limit this is something I see
everywhere and it's almost painful how
many places we write code that can block
forever yeah of course you know we we
have the obvious things like socket
communication where we use blocking
reads and writes and all it would take
is one function call on the socket
itself to set Esso timeout and you could
avoid having reads and writes block
forever without incurring the complexity
of ni oh yeah but then we also see
things like checking out resources from
a resource pool is usually done with no
timeout I think this is always a bad
idea
you should be you should set a timeout
on your resource pools and have the
application code be prepared to receive
a null response right when there's no
connection of a line makes your code a
little bit more complex because you have
to handle them now but I guess that's
what it takes to build stable systems
see exactly exactly right bulkheads
what's that I know the term from
aviation czar that's why I'm asking I'm
using it in the nautical sense uh-huh
bulkhead being a partition that prevents
flooding in one compartment from causing
flooding in another area yeah and so
generally speaking bulkheads are about
partitioning a system for stability
we've we've had a lot of talk recently
about horizontal partitioning for
scalability yeah but in this case what
I'm really saying is if I accept that
damage will happen and bad things are
going to occur to my system what I
really want to do is make sure that bad
things can occur in one part of it while
I maintain service for the rest of the
the rest of the system yeah and I think
this is particularly important for
anyone who's building a common services
or shared services component in an SOA
or just as an enterprise service because
ultimately everything will be
operationally and functionally coupled
to that shared service so any downtime
or lack of availability in that shared
service has a ripple effect throughout
the enterprise yeah and finally the last
one I kind of don't really know what it
means is this decoupling middleware
stuff I mean sure I know what what
middleware isn't I know what decoupling
is all about
but what do you mean in this in this
context well decoupling middleware it's
it's essentially a rant which says most
of the problems that I've described
throughout this section are due to our
use of synchronous request and response
types antics yeah so decoupling
middleware is an argument for messaging
tuple spaces and essentially you know
asynchronous sort of fire-and-forget yes
because in those environments for
example you have to work with timeouts
because you need to say how long do I
wait for a response so it's more natural
there it is more natural and the the
sort of
shock-absorbing characteristics of the
message cubes
allow you to decouple the operational
availability of the sender and receiver
right yeah anything else I forgot to ask
in a stability area anything else you
want to say they're the only the last
one that I would offer is the one that I
the stability pattern I call fail fast
we very often build systems that aren't
very aware of themselves they don't know
how well they're performing they don't
know what their internal state is they
sort of blindly attempt to do the
processing for whatever the request is
and sometimes do quite a bit of work
before ultimately failing and that can
be you know an application-level fail
you're like bad input parameters or it
can be a system level failure like I
can't talk to the database right now
it's been hit by a meteor so fail fast
is is my argument to say as soon as you
receive a request for work check your
own performance against SLA if you have
a two second response time and you're
monitoring yourself at 4 seconds or 10
or 30 seconds it's better to simply say
immediately yeah I cannot do this work
yeah likewise you can check the state of
your circuit breakers resource pools etc
and say I cannot do this work right now
it's better than trying to meet an SLA
deadline that's already passed right ok
second overall 10,000 foot aspect is
capacity and again I think it makes
sense to introduce what you mean by that
especially since you distinguish it from
scalability or performance so in terms
of capacity what I'm regarding is
capacity is the ability to perform a
certain workload mix within an
acceptable response time so this has a
relationship to performance and that the
better the application performs the
easier it is to maintain or sustain a
workload and it also crucially involves
the workload mix
so you know I've seen many times in
retail or insurance or hospitality
applications some types of users are
very cheap to service and some are very
expensive usually the ones that are
expensive to service are the ones who do
things that make you money buying things
reserving hotel rooms and say so the the
mix of workload is significant when when
we talk about capacity in this section
I'm trying to help maximize the capacity
that we can get out of an existing set
of resources right and so this is about
ways to look at the code itself and some
of the design characteristics to get as
much capacity as possible okay so let's
look at some of the things that then can
go wrong and they are a little bit some
of them are a little bit technology
specific right so maybe we should focus
on those that are not necessarily in
Java specific although of course that's
something a little bit the background of
your book they're some of both yeah you
know my book addresses Java and.net and
now generally speaking any kind of
online system right but most of my
examples are in Java because that's
where I've worked and I collected them
yeah so the ones that are fairly general
one that has a deleterious effect that
most people don't appreciate it the the
full magnitude of is contention for
resources in a resource pool and so we
always create resource pools as a way to
sort of cache those back-end connections
so we don't have to make a new
connection on every request but it turns
out when you have more concurrent
requests coming then you have things in
your resource pool the degradation is is
quite sharp and it accelerates quite
rapidly and it gets geometrically worse
when you introduce multiple resource
pools yeah so if a thread has to check
out connections from two different
resource pools then it's likely to
encounter contention on both yeah and
there's a feedback effect because when
it encounters contention on both that
lengthens the processing time of that
thread which means it's holding
resources for longer thus increasing the
likelihood of
their contention right yeah yeah
positive feedback another one I actually
find funny is HX overkill since I'm a
little bit of a web 2.0 skeptic or I
kind of dislike the hype this place very
nicely into my agenda kind of so so
what's that well so I I had initially
titled that section Ajax but as I looked
into it I discovered that Ajax can be
used for the good or for the ill of the
back-end system now where it's used for
the ill you see things like you know
pulling on keystrokes to do auto
completion of fields and things like
that which adds relatively little value
but vastly increases the number of
transactions at the backend has to
process and so you have the TCP set up
time you have you know thread checkout
time all the overhead incurred for what
might be just a tiny amount of actual
functional work yeah and it's that
overhead that concerns me yeah okay
hmm makes sense another one that I think
is interesting is how handcrafted SQL is
that your experience that people don't
really understand SQL and therefore
create queries that are kind of
ineffective or inefficient or what's the
point here for far beyond ineffective
they create queries that are downright
horrifying we have very good Oh our
tools these days yeah and all of them
have this escape hatch that lets you
create your own SQL and submit it
directly and sort of since because we've
got good are our tools the handcrafted
SQL tends to be stuff that's already
hairy and difficult you know it's it's
already sort of outside of the normal
realm of things otherwise the ORM Apple
could do it exactly
so you see things like eight-way unions
yeah where every clause of the Union has
a you know four table join in it I see a
lot of things like that where somebody
has tried to say
databases are really good at this type
of work so I'm gonna make sure I push as
much of it into the database as possible
and so they create this you know several
page
I just had one emailed to me last night
in fact that was utterly ridiculous I
couldn't find a font size that would
show me the whole thing so what you do
there I mean do you do load the data and
then do the computation in memory or is
it about denormalization and keeping the
denormalized tables kind of in sync or
well in almost every case I find that
the the handcrafted sequel tells me that
there's some missing abstraction there's
something that's not being represented
in the database or as objects or in
memory that ought to be and so usually
the first thing I do is try to tease out
what the what the true underlying
abstraction is and see if there's a way
to reify that in the object layer or in
the database layer another one that that
kind of - so to sum this up which is a
funny title is Cookie Monster's I just
you know I just imagine the big monster
next to the big table of cookies yeah
part part of trying to name patterns is
to find people will remember yeah yeah
you know country yeah
so the Cookie Monster is a site which
abuses cookies and tries to put too much
data in them so I've seen this even
recently where a retailer was trying to
create a persistent shopping cart so you
could add some things go away for a
month and when you came back your cart
would still have the things in it on the
premise that you actually you know
expect to buy everything that you put in
your cart so and they were doing this by
taking the shopping cart object
serializing it you you encoding it and
putting it in a cookie mm-hmm the cookie
was sometimes exceeding 4k in length so
some proxy servers would cut it off some
browsers wouldn't handle it well and if
you think about the way that the the
cookies get sent they get sent on every
request right that domain yeah whether
you need it for that or not so even once
the cart was deserialized
this 4k chunk was being sent down and up
on on every request yeah that adds time
and processing and memory and so on it
and of course the right way to work with
cookies is to put an index into them and
put the data in the database and garbage
collected at that time capacity patterns
what's the positive stuff you can do
first when you mention is pool
connections that's kind of obvious right
I mean everybody does that so there must
be something more to that how to do it
right or I don't know well so not
necessarily
I mean sometimes we document patterns
because they're apparently done not
because they're you know new or unique
right pooling connections is obviously
important we do it to the database all
the time we do it somewhat less often
when we're communicating with other
enterprise systems but it's worth doing
there as well right the other one is to
use caching carefully which I find is an
interesting name because it suggests
that caching is good because you should
use it but then it says carefully so
there was a bit trade-off there is in
fact at various times as I was writing
the book caching appeared as an
anti-pattern as a pattern or even both
yeah
and that's because it can be both so we
add caches to speed up response times
and avoid traffic to the database and
yet most application servers they don't
get CPU bound they are typically memory
bound and so when traffic gets heavy its
memory that gets short first and at that
point this large cache that we've got
that's supposed to be speeding things up
increases stress on garbage collection
and therefore slows down the whole
system right so I definitely believe in
using caching but I believe that the
caches should be elastic right they
should be willing to give up space when
memory gets tight and we can do this
through language features that make the
weak reference weak references soft
references those things that make the
the garbage collector people cringe hi
Kirk Pepperdine was covering his face
when I was talking about soft references
yeah so we can make the caches elastic
and that certainly helps the most common
kind of cache is just a hash map yeah
which gives us no ability to limit size
right and no ability to gracefully
release memory as as we need to so I
we need to move away from that and have
maybe at least a wrapper around the
hashmap that keeps track off the amount
of stuff in it and then don't accept
anymore and yes a very interesting
development that's come up since I wrote
the book is the use of cache servers and
I'm cache farms memcache you can use
Giga spaces that way you can coherence
ricotta that way yeah these I think are
a very significant development so what
do they do well as a cache server is
essentially just a big bunch of ram with
a socket in front of it and you can put
things into it and you can get things
out of that different ones have
different levels of capability around
distributed representation and so on but
in essence what they allow you to do is
pull all of that memory out of the JVM
and offload it to another box that may
be nothing but a huge amount of RAM
we're hearing people say Ram is the new
disc and the disc is the new tape
there's also this thing I think it's
called real layer or delay or something
there is a tool in Java that well there
are people who say forget databases put
everything in memory dump it in the
evening and if it crashes you have a
failover machine that's kind of the same
tendency right yeah the the use of RAM
for long-term storage yeah and I mean
you can buy a couple of gigabytes for
cheap money and not everybody has a
gigabyte database right so it's kind of
realistic in fact their vendors now who
are selling caching appliances which is
just one you pizza boxes stuffed with
half a terabyte of RAM yeah
half a terabyte of RAM yeah yeah the
other benefit that these offer though is
an efficiency one in terms of redundancy
so if you think about caching say all of
the hotels in your hotel chain you might
cache those in memory in the JVM if
you're in a horizontally scaled
application server farm then your
caching that entire list you know n
times where n is the number of instances
that you're running
that seems a little redundant right I'm
essentially chewing up you know 300 Meg
of heap 20 or 30 times now well but if
you have it Anna central shared location
there is more overhead to access it
right there is you you do give up a
little bit of latency but even giving up
that latency you're gaining a lot of
capacity right
yeah that's by the way that's a
trade-off that you have to do quite
often in order to get better overall
capacity you have to maybe reduce the
efficiency of each single specific
action or whatever it is absolutely
I completely agree anything else you
want to mention on capacity before we
move on to the next one one more that I
would offer is about pre computing
content mm-hmm
we have this tendency when we're talking
with our users that people who create
content for our systems or change prices
or you know feed the data into the
system we have this tendency to set an
expectation that their changes are
instantly visible everywhere in the
world and we build things that way so we
build pages dynamically on on every
request but we often don't need to do
that right so for instance I saw a site
where they had a sort of category
navigation structure tabs across the top
when you hover over the tab you see
subcategories listed underneath it yeah
those subcategories can change so they
were querying the database every time to
build that category tree yeah once a
month tree that you're pulling out of a
relational database so it's a little
8,000 queries on every single page to
build the menu the thing is we know
exactly when it changes there's a
content tool that publishes those
changes it's not as if you know we could
be caught unaware that the categories
have changed yeah and so I like to look
at the number of times something changes
versus the number of times it's being
viewed yep and in a case like this the
things were being viewed literally
sometimes nearly a billion times for
every time that they were changing yeah
it makes no sense to build it
dynamically every time I'm much better
off precomputing that content publishing
the content and just spooling it out
over there it's a little bit related to
this thing we talked about before where
I mentioned the intentional
denormalization
because that's basically precomputing
content in the database layer exactly
right and and then there is this other
thing where while ago actually I think
three years ago which or something or
two years I talked to Vella phobias
about Amazon stuff and he said that one
of the pillars of building large
distributed systems is to defer the
consistency to basically give up some
consistency some real timey behavior in
order to make it more scalable and
that's also something in that space yes
it is and and that's also an area where
there's been a lot of very interesting
developments over the last couple of
years maybe maybe will be for the next
book yeah okay no no no no promises yeah
next topic is operations again your ear
today working mainly as an operator so
meaning as somebody who operates
software in the operations department
why don't you give us a little bit of an
overview of what people can do right
what they can do wrong to make your life
harder or easier or simpler sure what I
found is a lot of software is failure
inducing that is it provokes the
operators into doing the wrong thing
uh-huh
and I have an example from from one of
my own systems where I found that
operations had instituted a regime of
restarts of recycling the application
servers whenever they saw a message that
said maximum entropy limit reached
channel reset required one time they had
observed that message in the log file
immediately prior to a system crash okay
and so they formed the superstitious
belief that that message indicated the
crash it was coincidental but they
instituted monitoring
an automated response that would restart
any time they saw that message well I
was horrified because I had written that
message and it had nothing at all to do
with resetting the server yeah it was
just talking about resetting the crypto
key for a communication channel yeah I
recently read Snyder's excellent book on
implementing that sort of thing right so
what I came to realize is that we very
often log messages that we intend for
ourselves for developers but in fact the
audience of log files is operations well
the audience of some of the log files
because you can also use log files for
for tracing bucks you can yeah so
anything that's logged as error severe
warning or info that is for operations
okay yeah and so we need to be cognizant
of how we write the messages so you know
that we don't encourage them to do the
wrong thing especially because we often
don't deliver a complete list of all the
messages that our applications can
produce yeah I mean I've been asked for
that many times and I always fight back
even though I know how useful it is to
receive one yeah yeah but I mean logging
generally is a good thing right I mean
it's necessary for the operations folks
to be able to understand the system
absolutely in fact logging remains the
primary tool that operations uses to
understand the system right and then of
course they have monitors that lock the
log output stream and define rules of
what to do when something occur exactly
yeah so it's also important that the
lock is structured well enough so that
you can define automated rules that do
something with it yes in fact one of the
things that I advocate is creating
message codes right yeah this is
something that you know was always there
in the mainframe days kind of
disappeared in the old world yeah yeah
and I have a section in the book that
offers a good trick on how you can
create message codes very easily and
produce that that reference document of
every message that the application can
produce probably about hashing the error
message or something
no it's using the internationalization
tools
okay extract all the strings okay hmm
okay another thing that I that I think
is interesting is the know where I
should ask the question the other way
around how important is it that your
system provides hooks for various
management tools you know the the
various IP based protocols that are
defined or Java Java management API or
something so it it used to be that SNMP
was the thing that we aimed for yeah
and I've experimented with creating
custom MIBs for my applications so that
they could be the mayor busy definition
of all the variables and tables that are
exposed through the management layer
kind of an interface definition of how
the MANET monitoring tool access your
system yes exactly so I've experimented
with that but what I found is operations
people will never accept a custom move
from the development group okay not ever
they're very protective of their
monitoring system and they should be
because if anything happens to that they
are blind yeah so that turns out not to
be a very profitable approach but for
anyone working in the Java world JMX is
certainly valuable and exposing the
state of your application through JMX is
something that I strongly advocate it is
possible also to get JMX to SNMP bridges
adapters so if you're exposing through
JMX then you also have the ability to
expose through SNMP right anything else
in operations that you want to mention
here one thing that I do have to bring
up a sort of a hot topic of mine or a
rant of mine relates to configuration
files uh-huh so I've done a lot of work
with things like spring where we've
externalized configuration into what
sometimes a very large file and we
deliver that file inside of our
application itself so inside the war
file or inside of your file that
configuration file has a number of
drawbacks one it's extremely sensitive
to
syntax so if a non programmer gets in
there and you know removes a single
quote character or misplace as a single
right bracket the entire file breaks
yeah second it mixes together the
essential plumbing of the application
ride with configurable parameters that
administrators I was actually about to
protest when you set configuration file
in the context of spring because the
beans XML isn't really what I would call
a configuration file for exactly that
reason because it's application wiring
as opposed to parametrizing whatever
queue size and stuff well but it mixes
all of it together in a single file and
that's a problem for spring fortunately
there is a thing called the property
override configure right which lets you
create an external file that overrides
individual properties of individual
beans yeah this has several benefits
first of all it lets you create a file
that's more robust it's just name equals
value priors it lets you create a file
that lives someplace else so it's not
overwritten with every deployment it
doesn't have to be hand edited every
time you do a new release yeah
and it lets the administrators keep
control of things like production
database passwords that have to be
treated with the highest level of
security than it is yeah I guess it's
really useful to see X well I mean you
know this trend towards XML instead of
source code is I'm not sure if I like it
but clearly there are some parts of xml
based specifications like sam'l right
the UI thing or also spring beans XML
that is effectively source code and not
a configuration file you need to
separate those and that's basically just
what you said yes I completely agree now
okay so we've stepped through the the
three main topics there is also a bunch
of let's say general issues that didn't
fit into one of those categories is
there anything you want to mention from
those that are kind of worth
highlighting of course we want to tell
people all by the book but them well
yeah so the general design issues
section did end up as sort of a holding
place for topics that are important to
creating production-ready software
that don't fit the structure anywhere
else right so one of them for example is
about the way we open sockets every
textbook and every tutorial on opening
sockets is wrong it's simply wrong why I
mean several clients up its server okay
the reason being a server in a data
center today has more than one network
interface hmm it always will typically
you'll have two for production traffic
and these may be team do they may go to
entirely different switches and then
you'll often also see management
interfaces and backup interfaces that
have their own IP addresses and they're
on separate networks and yet when you
open a socket and you don't specify
which interface you're opening it on if
you only open a socket with a port
number you're listening on all of them
which is rarely what you want to do yeah
because the security structure of the
backend networks is often much flatter
than the security structure of the
front-end network yeah so I've seen
order management systems with ports that
you could send XML into for orders and
it would the order management system
would trust the pricing that the
front-end was trying to send to it and
yet it listened on all of the interfaces
including the flat backup Network mm-hmm
so anyone who had any access to any
machine backed up over the network could
connect to this socket and submit orders
just by using netcat or something like
that had to send a chunk of xml yeah
certainly not what you want clearly not
the intended behavior yeah you have a
like mini section on security right I
mean I guess getting security right is
also a challenge that's bigger than most
of us developers probably think it is
bigger and I don't give security a full
treatment yeah but I do address you know
some of the very basics and for instance
please don't write any more applications
that have to run as root yeah so the
last thing I want to briefly mention is
this thing about load balancing and
clustering yesterday
didn't interview with Owen woods and he
said that one of the top ten
architectural mistakes is that people
think they can build their own clusters
quickly you know we can do it better
than WebSphere so I guess one of the
recommendations here is probably not to
do this in fact I never imagined that
people actually would try to build their
own clustering soft yeah well it's not
really clustering but a replication and
and you know failover and stuff instead
of using what the server's come with no
I I definitely would advocate using the
the well proven and tested
infrastructure from from the application
vendors yeah so I about both being part
of a cluster and using clustered
resources so for instance if your
application calls a database which is a
in any sort of an active/passive
failover cluster unexpected things may
happen when the cluster fails over so
for instance the virtual IP address may
be handed off to the passive node as
it's becoming active your application
may not be aware that the IP address now
belongs to somebody else yeah and you
typically don't have stateful failover
of all the connections yet so the you
know database connection you've been
using just fine all along suddenly stops
working all together yeah or magically
has different stuff in the database
because it wasn't replicated in time
that is possible do okay so I guess this
this brings us to the end of the of the
discussion and I don't know
there-there's a podcast called the space
show and the guy who runs the podcast
always asks his guests at the end of the
show whether they have any pearls of
wisdom that the guest wants to leave
with the listeners so I've kind of made
it a habit to also ask this is there
anything you want to leave our listeners
with except of course they should buy
the book and read the details well I'd
like to think I put all of my wisdom
into the hole but the the one thing I
would I would leave your listeners with
is this it's it's my plea really to
consider the entire lifecycle of the the
project and not to take shortcuts during
development to save a one-time
development cost at the expense of an
ongoing operational call right
yeah well I did that just to I mean you
shouldn't reply her but I mean of course
if you have different budgets and the
development guys don't care about the
other ones this can be a hard sell that
can be an organizational problem yes
debugging knows is outside the scope of
my book okay that's a nice closing word
thanks for being on the show thank you
[Music]
thanks for downloading and listening to
software engineering radio software
engineering radio is an educational
program brought to you by hillside
Europe if you want more information
about the podcast and all the other
episodes visit our website and s/ii -
radio dot length if you want to support
us you can donate to the SU radio team
via the website or you can advertise for
su radio for example by clicking on the
Digg reddit delicious and slash dot
buttons to contact the team please send
email to team @ SE - radio net or if it
is specific to an episode please use the
comments facility on the website so
other people can react to your comments
this episode of se radio as well as all
other episodes are licensed under
creative commons 2.5 license please see
the website for details thanks to
Charlie Crowell and the pod safe music
Network for the music used in the show
the song is called Vegas hard rock
shuffle
[Music]